<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Nostromo Chapter 8</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion from Juxta comparison set to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
                    <name>Generated by Juxta Commons</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <variantEncoding location="internal" method="parallel-segmentation"/>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <front>
            <div>
                <listWit>
                    <witness xml:id="wit-2242">versioning1TPsChapter8</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="wit-2241">versioning1HarpersChapter8</witness>
                </listWit>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>After landing from his swim 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="punctuation" n="0"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="punctuation" n="1">,</rdg>
</app> Nostromo had scrambled up, all dripping, into the main quadrangle of the old fort 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="punctuation" n="3">;</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="punctuation" n="2">,</rdg>
</app> and there, 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="spelling">amongst</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="spelling">among</rdg>
</app> ruined bits of walls and rotting remnants of roofs and sheds, he had slept the day through. He had slept in the shadow of the mountains, in the white blaze of noon, in the stillness and solitude of that overgrown piece of land between the nearly closed oval of the harbor and the spacious semicircle of the gulf 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="place" n="1">, open broadly to the vast ocean</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="place" n="0"></rdg>
</app> . He lay as if dead. A rey-zamuro, appearing like a tiny black speck in the blue, stooped, circling prudently with a stealthiness of flight startling in a bird of that great size. The shadow of his 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="punctuation" n="6">pearly-white</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="punctuation" n="0">pearly white</rdg>
</app> body, of his black-tipped wings, fell on the grass no more silently than he alighted himself on a hillock of rubbish within three yards of that man 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="punctuation" n="2">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="punctuation" n="0"></rdg>
</app> lying as still as a corpse. He stretched his bare neck, craned his bald head, loathsome in the brilliance of varied 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="spelling">colouring</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="spelling">coloring</rdg>
</app> , with an air of voracious anxiety towards the promising stillness of that prostrate body. Then 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="punctuation" n="2">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="punctuation" n="0"></rdg>
</app> sinking his head deeply into his soft plumage 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="punctuation" n="2">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="punctuation" n="0"></rdg>
</app> he settled himself to wait. The first thing upon which Nostromo's eyes fell on waking was this patient watcher for the signs of death and corruption. When the man got up the vulture hopped away in great, 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="punctuation" n="6">side-long</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="punctuation" n="0">sidelong</rdg>
</app> , fluttering jumps. He lingered for a while 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="punctuation" n="2">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="punctuation" n="0"></rdg>
</app> morose and reluctant 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="punctuation" n="2">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="punctuation" n="0"></rdg>
</app> before he rose, circling noiselessly with a sinister droop of beak and claws. <lb/>
Long after he had vanished the 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="epithet" n="1">Capataz</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="epithet" n="1">capataz</rdg>
</app> of the 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="epithet" n="1">Cargadores</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="epithet" n="1">cargadores</rdg>
</app> , lifting his eyes up to the sky, muttered, "I am not dead yet." <lb/>
Nostromo was some time in regaining his hold on the world. It had slipped from him completely in the deep slumber of more than twelve hours. It had been like a break of continuity in the chain of experience; he had to find himself in time and space, to think of the hour and the place of his return. It was a novelty. He was one of those efficient sailors who generally wake up from a dead sleep with their wits in complete working order. The 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="epithet" n="1">Capataz</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="epithet" n="1">capataz</rdg>
</app> of the 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="epithet" n="1">Cargadores</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="epithet" n="1">cargadores</rdg>
</app> had been a good man on board ship. He had been a good 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="punctuation" n="0">foremast hand</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="punctuation" n="6">foremast-hand</rdg>
</app> and a first-rate boatswain. 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="addition">That sort of excellence carries its own reward of satisfied vanity.</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241"></rdg>
</app> From the conditions of 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="addition">sea life it</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">sea-life that sort of excellence</rdg>
</app> brings no prize but an exaggerated consciousness of one's value and the confidence of one's superiors. The captain of the Genoese ship from which he had deserted had gone about tearing his 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="spelling">grey</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="spelling">gray</rdg>
</app> hairs with grief and exasperation. He 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="omission"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="addition">did it very publicly, being an Italian and unashamed of genuine emotions. He</rdg>
</app> mingled imprecations against ingratitude with words of regret at his loss before the people on the wharf, before the lightermen discharging the cargo; in the O.S.N. office before Captain Mitchell 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="punctuation">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="punctuation"></rdg>
</app> who was sympathetic in a way, but considered him in the end an awful and ridiculous nuisance 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="punctuation">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="punctuation"></rdg>
</app> and was glad to see his back for the last time. <lb/>
Nostromo, in close hiding in a back room of a pulperia for the three days before the ship sailed, heard of these lamentations, threats, and curses apparently unmoved. But he heard of them with satisfaction. This was as it should be. He was a valuable man. What better recognition could he expect? His vanity was infinitely and naively greedy, but his conceptions were limited. Afterwards his success in the work he found on shore enlarged them in the direction of personal magnificence. This sailor led a public life in his sphere. It became necessary to him. It was the very breath of his nostrils. And who can say that it was not genuine distinction 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="punctuation" n="4">?</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" n="1">.</rdg>
</app> It was genuine because it was based on something that was in him -- his 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">overweening</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">over-weening</rdg>
</app> vanity, which Decoud alone, thinking that he would be of use politically, had taken the trouble to find out. Each man must have some temperamental sense by which to discover himself. With Nostromo it was vanity of an artless sort. 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">Without it he would have been nothing.</rdg>
</app> It called out his recklessness, his industry, his ingenuity, and that disdain of the natives which helped him so much upon the line of his work and resembled an inborn capacity for command. It made him appear incorruptible and fierce. It made him happy also. He was 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">disinterested with the un-worldliness of a sailor, arising not so much from the absence of mercenary instincts as from sheer ignorance and carelessness for to-morrow.    He was</rdg>
</app> pleased with himself. It was not the cold, ferocious, and idealistic self-conceit of a man of some northern race; it was materialistic and imaginative. It was an unpractical and warm sentiment, a picturesque development of his character, the growth of an unsophisticated sense of his individuality. It was immense. It was fostered by Captain Mitchell's absurd pride in his foreman , the varied use made of his handiness, and the appreciative grunts and nods of the silent old Viola, to whose exalted sentiments every sort of faithfulness appealed greatly. <lb/>
The 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">Capataz</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">capataz</rdg>
</app> of the Sulaco 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">Cargadores</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">cargadores</rdg>
</app> had lived in 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">splendour</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">splendor</rdg>
</app> and publicity up to the very moment, as it were, when he took charge of the lighter containing the treasure in silver ingots. <lb/>
The last act he had performed in Sulaco was in complete harmony with his vanity, and as such perfectly genuine. He had given his last 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">dollar</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">quarter-dollar</rdg>
</app> to an old woman moaning with the grief and fatigue of a dismal search under the arch of the ancient gate. Performed in obscurity and without witnesses, it had still the 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">characteristic</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">characteristics</rdg>
</app> of 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">splendour</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">splendor</rdg>
</app> and publicity, and was in strict keeping with his reputation. But this awakening, in solitude but for the watchful vulture, 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">amongst</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">among</rdg>
</app> the ruins of the fort 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">,</rdg>
</app> had no such characteristics. His first confused feeling was exactly this -- that it was not in keeping. It was more like the end of things. 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">The necessity of living concealed somehow, for God knows how long, which assailed him on his return to consciousness, made everything that had gone before for years appear vain and foolish, like a flattering dream come suddenly to an end.</rdg>
</app> <lb/>He climbed the crumbling slope of the rampart 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241"></rdg>
</app> and, putting aside the bushes, looked upon the 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">harbour</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">harbor</rdg>
</app> . He saw a couple of ships at anchor upon the sheet of water reflecting the last gleams of light 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">,</rdg>
</app> and Sotillo's steamer moored to the jetty. And behind the pale 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">,</rdg>
</app> long front of the 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">Custom House</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">custom-house</rdg>
</app> there appeared the extent of the town 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">,</rdg>
</app> like a grove of thick timber on the plain 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">,</rdg>
</app> with a 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">gateway</rdg>
</app> in front 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241"></rdg>
</app> and the cupolas 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="place" n="0"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="place" n="1">, towers,</rdg>
</app> and miradors 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">of churches</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241"></rdg>
</app> rising above the trees, all dark, as if surrendered already to the night. The thought that it was no longer open to him to ride through the streets, 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242" type="spelling">recognised</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241" type="spelling">recognized</rdg>
</app> by everyone, great and little, as he used to do every evening on his way to play monte in the posada of the Mexican Domingo 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">;</rdg>
</app> or 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">, sitting</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">to sit</rdg>
</app> in the place of 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">honour</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">honor</rdg>
</app> , 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">listening</rdg>
</app> to 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">listen to</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241"></rdg>
</app> songs and 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">look</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">looking</rdg>
</app> at dances, made it appear to him as a town that had no existence. <lb/>
For a long time he gazed on, then let the parted bushes spring back, and 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241"></rdg>
</app> crossing over to the other side of the fort, surveyed the vaster emptiness of the great gulf. The Isabels stood out heavily upon the narrowing long band of red in the west, which gleamed low between their black shapes 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">;</rdg>
</app> and the 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">Capataz</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">capataz</rdg>
</app> thought of Decoud alone there with the treasure. That man was the only one who cared whether he fell into the hands of the Monterists or not, the 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">Capataz</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">capataz</rdg>
</app> reflected bitterly. And that merely would be an anxiety for his own sake. As to the rest, they neither knew nor cared. What he had heard Giorgio Viola say once was very true. Kings, ministers, 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">the</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241"></rdg>
</app> aristocrats, the rich in general, kept the people in poverty and subjection; they kept them as they kept dogs, to fight and hunt for their service. <lb/>
The darkness of the sky had descended to the line of the horizon, enveloping the whole gulf, the islets, and the lover of Antonia 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">,</rdg>
</app> alone with the treasure on the Great Isabel. The 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">Capataz</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">capataz</rdg>
</app> of the 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">Cargadores</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">cargadores</rdg>
</app> , turning his back on these things invisible and existing, sat down and took his face between his fists. He felt the pinch of poverty for the first time in his life. 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">To find himself without money after a run of bad luck at monte in the low, smoky room of Domingo&apos;s posada, where the fraternity of cargadores gambled, sang, and danced of an evening; to remain with empty pockets after a burst of public generosity to some peyne d&apos;oro girl or other (for whom he did not care), had none of the humiliation of destitution. He remained rich in glory and reputation.	But since it was no longer possible for him to parade the streets of the town and be hailed with respect in the usual haunts of his leisure, this sailor felt himself destitute indeed.</rdg>
</app> <lb/>His mouth was dry. It was dry with heavy sleep and extremely anxious thinking 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241"></rdg>
</app> as it had never been dry before. It may be said that Nostromo tasted the dust and ashes of the fruit of life into which he had bitten deeply in his hunger for praise. Without removing his head from between his fists he tried to spit before him -- "Tfui" -- and muttered a curse upon the selfishness of all the rich people. <lb/>
In this 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">harbour</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">harbor,</rdg>
</app> at the foot of immense mountains that outlined their 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">shadowy</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241"></rdg>
</app> peaks 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">amongst</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">among</rdg>
</app> the kindled swarm of stars 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">;</rdg>
</app> on this smooth, half-wild sheet of black water 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">,</rdg>
</app> serene in its loneliness, whose future of crowded prosperity was being settled not so much by the industry as by the fears 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">and</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">,</rdg>
</app> necessities and crimes of men 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241"></rdg>
</app> short-sighted in good and evil, the two solitary foreign ships had hoisted their 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">riding lights</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">riding-lights,</rdg>
</app> according to rule. But Nostromo gave no second look to the 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">harbour</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">harbor</rdg>
</app> . Those two ships were present enough to his mind. Either would have been a refuge. It would have been no feat for him to swim off to them. One of them was an Italian 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">barque</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">bark</rdg>
</app> which had brought a cargo of timber from Puget Sound for the railway. He knew her men; in his quality of foreman of all the work done in the 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">harbour</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">harbor</rdg>
</app> he had been able to oblige her captain in some small matter relating to the filling of his 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">water tanks</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">water-tanks</rdg>
</app> . Bronzed, black-whiskered, and stately, with the impressive gravity of a man too powerful to unbend 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">in a smile</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241"></rdg>
</app> , he had been invited more than once to drink a glass of Italian vermouth in her cabin. It was well known 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">amongst</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">among</rdg>
</app> ship-masters trading along the seaboard that 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">,</rdg>
</app> as a matter of sound policy 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242"> </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">,</rdg>
</app> the 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">Capataz</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">capataz</rdg>
</app> of 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">Cargadores</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">the cargadores</rdg>
</app> in Sulaco should be propitiated by small civilities, which 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">, as a matter of fact,</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241"></rdg>
</app> he seemed to expect as his due. For in truth, being implicitly trusted by Captain Mitchell, he had, as somebody said, the whole 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">harbour</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">harbor</rdg>
</app> in his pocket. For the rest, an excellent fellow, quite 
<app>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2242">straightforward</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#wit-2241">straight-forward</rdg>
</app> , everybody agreed.<lb/>
</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
